Guide to the Francis B. (Francis Butler) Loomis Papers: microfilm, 1897-1939
Department of Special Collections
Francis B. (Francis Butler) Loomis Papers: microfilm,
1897-1939
Special Collections M0096
Loomis, Francis B. (Francis Butler), 1861-1948.
7.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Official and personal correspondence, reports, legal briefs, speeches, publications, photographs, newspaper clippings, and miscellaneous material; also included is correspondence dealing with Loomis' involvement in crises relating to Venezuela, Santo Domingo, and Panama, his role during negotioation of the Russo-Japanese War, and his participation in Republan politics during the years 1898-1912; post World War I correspondence focuses on such varied topics as the Japanese question in California, the importance of newspapers in forming public opinion, and consular reform and political issues; numerous Presidents of the U.S. and other notable figures of the period are represented.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 24 hours in advance of intended use.
Acquisition Information
The major portion of the collection was given by Miss Florence I. Loomis in April 1964. The bound volumes of outgoing correspondence and a number of books were given to the Hoover Institution in April 1962. In 1964 these items were transferred from Hoover and added to Miss Loomis' gift to Special Collections.
Biographical Note
Francis B. Loomis' service with the State Department came during a critical period in American history. Both at home and abroad, he helped mold policy at a time when the Spanish-American War was being fought, when Japan was beginning to feel her strength in the Pacific, when the preliminary maneuvers for the construction of the Panama Canal were in progress, and when American economic imperialism was at its height. The diplomatic phase of his career seemed remarkable, but he was no less successful in his other varied endeavors. Loomis enjoyed success as a newspaper man, a political publicist, and a key figure in the U.S. oil industry.
Loomis' ancestors came to Windsor, Connecticut, from Braintree, England, in 1638 as part of the Puritan emigration from England. The family home at Windsor still stands as the Loomis Institute, dedicated to offering free education to deserving youngsters from twelve to twenty years old. Mr. Loomis, born in Marietta, Ohio, on July 27, 1861, was the son of Judge William B. and Frances (Wheeler) Loomis. He graduated from Marietta College in 1883 and joined the staff of the New York Tribune shortly thereafter. His involvement with politics began at the relatively early age of twenty-three when he worked on the James G. Blaine campaign of 1884 as head of the press bureau of the Republican National Committee. In this position Loomis was able to form friendships with Mr. Blaine, Senator Foraker, and many leaders of the Republican party. After Blaine's defeat, Loomis returned to Ohio to serve as State Librarian for two years. In 1887 he became the Washington correspondent for the Philadelphia Press. The following year Loomis reassumed his position as press agent for the Republican party's presidential nominee, Benjamin Harrison.
With President Harrison's victory, Loomis was appointed U.S. Consul to St. Etienne. France, a position he assumed in 1890. For the next three years he gave particular attention to the study of industrial conditions in Europe. Upon his return to the United States, he became Editor-in-Chief of the Cincinnati Daily Tribune. Once again Loomis was drafted to serve the Republican party. William McKinley called him to Canton. Ohio to aid his presidential campaign.
Shortly after his marriage to Elizabeth Mast of Springfield, Ohio he was appointed Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to Venezuela. Loomis' actions in Venezuela were either damned or praised, depending upon viewpoint. His detractors accused him of using American prestige and economic power to force business concessions abroad. His friends insisted that his only object was to improve trade relations between the United States and Venezuela. Loomis' service in Venezuela was quite active. He provided intelligence reports on the location of Admiral Cervera's fleet during the Spanish-American War; he explored trade possibilities during a trip up the Orinoco River aboard the Wilmington in 1898; he successfully negotiated several commercial treaties; and he energetically defended American interests in Venezuela.
In 1901 Loomis was appointed Minister to Portugal, a post he held until 1902 when he was recalled and appointed First Assistant Secretary of State. As First Assistant Secretary he served under John Hay, assuming more and more responsibility for the department as Hay's health deteriorated. With Hay's death in 1905, he became Secretary of State ad interim until Taft accepted the appointment. He was the first person to have served through all the grades of consular service and became its directing head in Washington.
Loomis was clearly a key figure in the implementation and formulation of Theodore Roosevelt's Panama policy. When it became clear that Colombia would not ratify the Hay-Herran treaty, he contacted John Basset Moore, an authority on international law, who concluded that Colombia was not in a position to obstruct the building of the canal. No doubt Loomis had been heavily influenced by Philippe Bunau-Varilla, whose commitment to the Panama route was decisive to the revolution. The two corresponded regularly from as early as 1902. Indeed, it is thought that it was Loomis who sent a telegram to the American representative in Panama to inform him that a revolution was in progress several hours before it had begun.
As Assistant Secretary, Loomis made many other major contributions to foreign policy. He played a large part in the settlement of the Santo Domingo financial problems of 1903, going to Santo Domingo to personally investigate and recommend solutions. He instigated and implemented the first trade agreement between the United States and Abyssinia. (It was while carrying this document to Abyssinia in 1904 aboard the Kaiser Wilhelm II that his brother, F. Kent Loomis, fell or was thrown overboard.) Loomis was closely connected with the negotiations which surrounded the Russo-Japanese War settlement. He weathered the scandal of the Bowen Affair. At the time of Hay's death he was in France as special envoy to claim the remains of John Paul Jones.
The strain of intense diplomatic activity, the Bowen Affair, and his brother's death took their toll. In October, 1905, Francis Loomis resigned as First Assistant Secretary of State with the understanding that he would be employed for special missions only. The succeeding years were occupied with speaking engagements, activities on behalf of the American Red Cross, and personal business. His interest in Japan and Japanese affairs, which developed as a result of his role during the Russo-Japanese negotiations, led to a presidential appointment in 1908 as special envoy to Japan and chairman of the American commission to plan participation in the Tokyo Exposition. More importantly, his presence in Japan was designed to remove any suggestion of menace, which President Roosevelt feared might be aroused in the minds of the Japanese people by his sending the American fleet around the world.
Upon his return to the United States, Loomis became involved with the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, and Republican politics. In 1912 he was appointed United States Commissioner General to the Exposition at Turin, Italy, and served in a similar capacity to the Berlin International Exposition Congress.
Always a newspaper man at heart, Loomis made an attempt to purchase the Oakland Tribune with Alfred Holman. The negotiations were unsuccessful. However, he was captivated by California and moved his family to Burlingame in 1914. Soon after, he joined the staff of Standard Oil Company as a foreign trade adviser. Though his position de manded that he travel extensively, he still managed active participation in California affairs. As a charter member of the Japanese Society of America, he endeavored to promote better relations between the Japanese and Caucasians in California. He visited Japan in 1922 and assisted in organizing a program to aid the Tokyo earthquake victims in 1923. Additionally, he continued his activities for the Republican Party, was a member of several clubs in the Bay Area, and continued his copious correspondence. Mr. Loomis retired from Standard Oil Company in 1941 at the age of eighty. He died on August 6, 1948.
His papers reveal the extent to which one individual may influence the path of history. A man recognized by his peers, but largely unfamiliar to the public, Loomis played a formative role in Republican politics and an aggressive U.S. foreign policy. His career illustrated his belief in fulfilling the Manifest Destiny of his generation.
Scope and Content
The Francis B. Loomis Papers reflect one of the most dynamic periods of American Historythe era of the Monroe Doctrine, of American imperialism, and of Theodore Roosevelt's political vitality. This collection includes official and personal correspondence, reports, legal briefs, speeches, publications, photographs, newspaper clippings, and miscellaneous material. Of particular importance is correspondence dealing with Loomis' involvement in crises relating to Venezuela, Santo Domingo, and the Panama Canal; his role during negotiation of the Russo-Japanese War; and his participation in Republican politics during the years 1898-1912.
Post World War I correspondence, ancillary to the main questions raised by the papers, focuses on such varied topics as the Japanese question in California, the importance of newspapers in forming public opinion, and of course, Loomis' continued interest in consular reform and political issues. Unfortunately, the collection suffers from some major omissions. Few items relate to Loomis' career with Standard Oil Company from 1914-1941. Additionally, there is a significant absence of correspondence between Mr. Loomis and Bunau-Varilla before November 12, 1903, although it is known that they corresponded as early as 1902.
These papers provide perspectives on issues which concern modern researchers, such as nationalism in the Canal Zone, U.S.-Latin American relations, the inner workings of the two party system, and effective consular representation abroad. Close examination of the material raises as many questions as it provides answers. This obvious paradox makes the Loomis Papers most valuable to the student of American history in that it provides important incentive for further investigation.
Editorial Procedures
The microfilm edition of the Francis B. Loomis Papers consists of nine rolls of film and represents six linear feet. It has been filmed in accordance with specifications of the Technical Standards for Microfilm Documentary Publication Projects prepared by the National Historical Publications and Records Commission.
The physical characteristics of this collection necessitated filming the incoming and cutgoing correspondence separately. Incoming letters have been arranged alphabetically by sender. Items with illegible signatures were placed at the end of the alphabetical sequence. The outgoing correspondence, much of which was contained in letterbooks, was arranged chronologically. Whenever possible, undated material was marked with a date enclosed in brackets. Where exact dating was not possible, the documents were placed at the end of the appropriate month or year. Indices of incoming and outgoing correspondence have been included in the microfilm edition.
In order to retain the integrity of the scrapbooks, certain correspondence and publications have been left in their original locations. Clippings, however, found in the scrapbooks have been arranged in loose chronological order, and placed following the book in which they were previously field.
Targets have been placed before documents to indicate a defective original, a fragment, folder numbers, and series titles. Original documents precede copies or translations. Enclosures follow the covering letter.
Those items such as photographs and scrapbooks that could not be included in a chronological framework were arranged by series. The collection has been dividend in the following manner: Incoming Correspondence; Outgoing Correspondence; Career Records; Biographical Information, Speeches, and Articles; Photographs; Scrapbooks and Clippings; and Descendants of Joseph Loomis in America.
Acknowledgements
The reorganization and microfilming of the Francis B. Loomis Papers were made possible by the support of the Tinker Foundation and the National Historical Publications and Records Commission. In providing financial assistance for this project, these organizations have made a valuable contribution to the dissemination of important historical information.
Patricia J. Palmer, head of the Manuscripts Division, has directed the Loomis project with her usual tact and patience. Michele Leiser's invaluable editorial suggestions merit special thanks, as do the efforts of our conscientious typists. Martha Lewis, Melinda Jalone, and Joan Zwiep. Grateful recognition is also due the Special Collections Department and the administrative offices of the Stanford University Libraries.
I would like to acknowledge the excellent and uncomplaining service rendered by Herb Larson, microphotographer, and the valuable assistance of James M'Guinness of the Stanford University Publications Service. As always, Fred Shelley of the National Historical Publications and Records Commission offered his encouragement and support.
Lynn M. Jimnez
Editor
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Barrett, John.; Beasley, Delilah L.; Bowen, Herbert.; Bryce, James, Viscount, 1838-1922.; Bunau-Varilla, Philippe, 1859_1940.; Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947.; Carnegie, Andrew, 1835-1919.; Davison, Henry Pomeroy.; Dolge, Rudolf.; Foraker, Joseph Benson, 1846-1917.; Griscom, Lloyd C.; Hanna, Marcus Alonzo, 1837-1904.; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923.; Harrison, Benjamin, 1833-1901.; Hay, John, 1838-1905.; Hill, David Jayne.; Holman, Alfred H.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948.; Hull, Cordell, 1871-; Jones, John Paul, 1747-1792.; Kahn, Julius, 1861-1924.; Kellogg, Frank B.; Knox, Philander.; Lodge, Henry Cabbot, 1850-1924.; Moore, John Bassett.; Morse, Samuel F. B.; Reid, J. Whitelaw, 1837-1912.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919.; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937.; Skinner, Robert Peet, 1866-1960.; Stimson, Henry Lewis, 1867-1950.; Straus, Oscar Solomon, 1850-1926.; Taft, Robert A.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930.; Thaddeus, Henry J.; Warren, Charles, 1868-1954.; Welles, Sumner, 1892-; Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927.; Young, Ella, 1867-1956.; Republican Party (U.S.).; Presidents--United States--Election.; Political conventions.; United States--Foreign relations.; Japan.; Panama Canal.; Portugal.; Venezuela.; Portraits
Collection Contents
- Incoming Correspondence, ca. 1900 - 1932, Series 1; 2 microfilm reels
  - Adee-Bryce (Reel 1, Folder 1)
  - Bunau-Varilla, P. (Reel 1, Folder 2)
  - Burleson-Conkling (Reel 1, Folder 3)
  - Conde-Diaz (Reel 1, Folder 4)
  - Dillingham-Durand (Reel 1, Folder 5)
  - The Economist Hammond (Reel 1, Folder 6)
  - Hanna-Hay (Reel 1, Folder 7)
  - Hays Hurst (Reel 1, Folder 8)
    This roll contains correspondence to Loomis and to others concerned with Loomis and or events in which he was involved. Roll I displays such correspondents as black educator Delilah L. Beasley, Nicholas Murray Butler, newspaperman Alfred Holman, John Hay, Andrew Carnegie, William H. Crocker, Senator J. B. Foraker, Charles Evans Hughes, and Carl B. Hurst. One of several highlights in this roll is a letter dated April 12, 1905, from Bunau-Varilla thanking Loomis for "the support you have given me in the most critical moment of my long effort towards the vindication of the Panama conception."
  - Holt-Leon (Reel 2, Folder 9)
  - Libby-Montauban (Reel 2, Folder 10)
  - Moore-Ohio Republican State Executive Committee (Reel 2, Folder 11)
  - O'Laughlin-Pillsbury (Reel 2, Folder 12)
  - Porter-Rodgers (Reel 2, Folder 13)
  - Roosevelt, T. (Reel 2, Folder 14)
  - Root-Shortridge (Reel 2, Folder 15)
  - Sigsbee-Skinner (Reel 2, Folder 16)
  - Smith-Thayer (Reel 2, Folder 17)
  - Thompson-Zumeta (Reel 2, Folder 18)
- Outgoing Correspondence, Letterbooks, 1903 - 1905, Series 2.1; 2 microfilm reels
  Most of this outgoing correspondence pertains to Loomis' daily business. Throughout the series of letterbooks one finds reference to the Mast ranch in California and to personal business of a mundane character. However, upon closer inspection several important notes can be discovered. One example is a letter dated June 3, 1903, in which Loomis suggests to Senator Mark Hanna that Bunau-Varilla would be willing to provide information on, and help with, the Panama treaty. Another note dated August 14, 1903, instructs John Basset Moore to prepare the famous memorandum on the Panama question for President Roosevelt. Other correspondence concerns the Pedicaris kidnapping, F. Kent Loomis' death, Santo Domingo, and the Bowen Affair.
  - February 12-October 27, 1903 (Reel 3, Reel-section 1)
  - October 28, 1903-July 13, 1904 (Reel 3, Reel-section 2)
  - July 14, 1904-February 20, 1905 (Reel 4, Reel-section 3)
  - February 21-August 28, 1905 (Reel 4, Reel-section 4)
  - August 29-October 11, 1905 (Reel 4, Reel-section 5)
- Outgoing Correspondence, ca. 1900 - 1932, Series 2.2; 0.6 microfilm reel
  - July 19, 1900-June 20, 1905 (Reel 5, Folder 19)
  - July 28, 1905-June 23, 1907 (Reel 5, Folder 20)
  - January - December 19, 1908 (Reel 5, Folder 21)
  - January 18-February 26, 1909 (Reel 5, Folder 22)
  - March 1, 1909-September 14, 1916 (Reel 5, Folder 23)
  - January 26, 1917-September 24, 1931 (Reel 5, Folder 24)
  - January 4, 1932Undated Correspondence (Reel 5, Folder 25)
- Career Records, 1892 - 1935, Series 3; ca. 2 microfilm reels
  - Bowen Affair: Charges, Statements, and Replies by Loomis (Reel 5, Folder 26)
  - Bowen Affair: Statements (Reel 5, Folder 27)
  - Bowen Affair: Testimony (Reel 5, Folder 28)
  - Bowen Affair: Mercado Claim (Reel 5, Folder 29)
  - Bowen Affair: Published Material (Reel 6, Folder 30)
  - Venezuela: Treaty of 1836 (Reel 6, Folder 31)
  - Venezuela: 1897-1936 (Reel 6, Folder 32)
  - Venezuela: Published Material 1892-1924 (Reel 6, Folder 33)
  - Panama Canal 1903-1934 (Reel 6, Folder 34)
    The Bowen Affair documents are continued on Roll VI, concluding with a published record of the case. The following career records consist of treaties, notes, and published material on Venezuela, and the Panama Canal. A notable item contained in the Venezuelan records is a peace treaty between the U.S. and Venezuela dated 1836. The Panama Canal material includes a booklet depicting the steps taken to build the canal.
  - Ethiopia (Abyssinia) 1904-1935 (Reel 7, Folder 35)
  - John Paul Jones Mission (Reel 7, Folder 36)
  - Santo Domingo 1905-1906 (Reel 7, Folder 37)
  - Japan 1903-1912 (Reel 7, Folder 38)
  - Miscellaneous Career Records (Reel 7, Folder 39)
- Biographical Information, Speeches, and Articles, ca. 1900 - ca. 1935, Series 4; 1.4 microfilm reels
  - Biographical Information (Reel 7, Folder 40)
  - Appointments and Honors (Reel 7, Folder 41)
  - Speeches by Loomis (Reel 7, Folder 42)
  - Miscellaneous Political Material (Reel 7, Folder 43)
  - Printed Speeches by Loomis (Reel 7, Folder 44)
  - Speeches by Mrs. Loomis (Reel 7, Folder 45)
  - Articles written by and about Loomis (Reel 8, Folder 46)
  - Proceedings of International Conference, American Society for Judicial Settlement of International Dispute (Reel 8, Folder 47)
- Photographs, 1888 - 1901, Series 5; 0.5 microfilm reels
  - Loomis Family Portraits (Reel 8, Folder 48)
  - Photographs (Reel 8, Folder 49)
  - Photographs (Reel 8, Folder 50)
  - Trip up Orinoco River 1898-99 (Reel 8, Folder 51)
  - Venezuela 1897-1901 (Reel 8, Folder 52)
  - Venezuela 1897-1901 (Reel 8, Folder 53)
- Scrapbook Clippings, 1899 - 1901; n.d., Series 6; 0.5 microfilm reels
  Roll VIII begins with articles written by and about Loomis. His contributions to the Independent define the government's position in Panama and Santo Domingo as he saw it. The article Our Diplomatic Science and its Needs was only one of his many efforts to improve the efficiency of the State Department. This roll contains photos and photo scrapbooks of newspaper clippings which have been arranged loosely by subject.
  - McKinley, Marriage, and Venezuela (Reel 8, Folder 54)
  - Venezuela 1899 (Reel 8, Folder 55)
  - Venezuela 1900-1901 (Reel 8, Folder 56)
  - Bowen Affair and Personal (Reel 8, Folder 57)
  - Portugal and Personal (Reel 8, Folder 58)
  - Panama and Santo Domingo (Reel 8, Folder 59)
  - John Paul Jones Mission (Reel 8, Folder 60)
  - Asia, Venezuela, and Personal (Reel 8, Folder 61)
  - Venezuela and Clippings (Reel 9, Folder 62)
- Miscellaneous, Keepsakes, Menus, Invitations, Programs, Postcards, and Autographs, n.d., Series 7; Not Photographed
  - Duplicate Documents (Reel 9, Folder 63)
  - Autographs (Reel 9, Folder 64)
  - Postcards (Reel 9, Folder 65)
  - Messages of the President (Reel 9, Folder 66)
  - Color Studies of the Pan-Pacific Expo (Reel 9, Folder 67)
  - Menus (Reel 9, Folder 68)
  - Christmas Cards and Calling Cards (Reel 9, Folder 69)
  - Invitations (Reel 9, Folder 70)
- Descendants of Joseph Loomis in America and His Antecedents in the Old World, Series 8; 1 microfilm reel
  Series 7. Miscellaneous, has not been photographed. A few clippings of Venezuela from Series VI precede the records of the Loomis family. Descendants of Joseph Loomis in America and His Antecedents in the Old World has been filmed in its entirety. This was done to provide background information on Loomis and his family, and to preserve the material presented in this scarce publication.
Index I
This index is a unified index to both the original collection as well as the microfrom collection. Each folder within the entire collection is numbered uniquely throughout the collection and is not repeated; therefore, the folder listed in the index entry serves as a unique identifier for the location of the materials, just as the roll number provides a unique reference to the roll in which the item is to be found.
See also index II
Abbot, [?] Roll I Folder 6 Roll II Folder 9
Abbot, Ernest Roll II Folder 15
Abbot, John T. Roll II Folder 11
Adams, Henry Roll II Folder 16, Folder 17
Adee, Alvey Roll I Folder 1, Folder 7, Folder 8 Roll II Folder 9, Folder 11, Folder 14, Folder 17
Ahlstrom, Carl Roll I Folder 4
Albright, Howard C. Roll II Folder 15
Alcal, F. Roll I Folder 1
Aldrich, Nelson W. Roll I Folder 6
Alenood, Harry J. Roll II Folder 9
Alessandri Palma, Arturo Roll II Folder 18
Alette, J. Roll II Folder 9
Alexander II, of Russia Roll I Folder 1
Algeciras, Conference of January 16, 1906 Roll II Folder 10
Alger, Russell A. Roll I Folder 8 Roll II Folder 13
Almond, Harry J. Roll I Folder 5, Folder 8 Roll II Folder 9
Amador Guerrero, Manuel Roll I Folder 1, Folder 2
American College Roll I Folder 4
American Library Association Board Roll I Folder 1
American Peace Society Roll I Folder 3
American Protective League Roll II Folder 13
American Red Cross Roll I Folder 1, Folder 6 Roll II Folder 12, Folder 14, Folder 17
American Red Cross Board of Incorporators Roll I Folder 1
American Steam Laundry Roll I Folder 5
American Tobacco Company Roll I Folder 3
Andrade, Ignacio Roll I Folder 1, Folder 8 Roll II Folder 17